<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xmlns:xi  CDATA  #FIXED 'http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude'">
]>

<sect1 id="runtime-build-linux" >
    <title>Compiling ANTLR on UNIX-like systems</title>

    <para>
      This chapter covers building and installing ANTLR on UNIX and
      UNIX-like systems such as Linux.<!-- Compiling ANTLR on Microsoft
      Windows is different in detail and somewhat more difficult to
      get going since the necessary tools aren't included with
      the operating system.-->
    </para>
    <!--para>
      Before we get into the details of how to compile ANTLR, we should
      mention that in many cases, binary packages of ANTLR prebuilt for
      your operating system will be available, either from your
      operating system vendor or from independent sources. If such a
      set of packages is available, installing it will get you
      programming wih ANTLR much faster than building it yourself. In
      fact, you may well already have ANTLR installed on your system
      already.
    </para-->
    <para>
        Is recommended for most users. Pre-compiled binaries of the
        stable ANTLR are usually available for many platforms
        (see the platform-specific pages for more details), so you
        do not even have to compile the code yourself.
    </para>


  <sect2 id="getting_source">
    <title>Get source code</title>

        <sect3 id="source_packages">
            <title>From the source package</title>
            <para>
                The official distribution of ANTLR is the source code,
                distributed in tar files from the antlr site.
                The same source code can be compiled to create binaries
                for different platforms such as GNU/Linux, Microsoft Windows,
                Mac OS X, Solaris and many others.
            </para>
            <para>
                A source package is distributed as a
                <literal>zip</literal>, <literal>tar.gz</literal> or <literal>tar.bz2</literal> file
                which you unpack into a directory full of the source files as follows:
            </para>
            <programlisting language="bash">tar xvfz ANTLR-4.5.3.tar.gz</programlisting>
            <programlisting language="bash" linenumbering="unnumbered">tar xvfj ANTLR-4.5.3.tar.bz2</programlisting>
            <para>
                It is available from the antlr site at <ulink url="http://www.antlr.org/download.html">C Target</ulink>.
            </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="git_repository">
            <title>From the Git repository</title>

            <para>
                The repository contains several versions of the code called <literal>branches</literal>
                so you can fetch the latest version (<literal>master</literal>) or a stable version
                from a maintenance branch. If you intend to contribute to the
                development of ANTLR, then you should try using Git. As the code is
                constantly evolving and features are added (or removed) every day,
                you should have a look at the developers’ site and subscribe to the
                <ulink role="online-location" url="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/antlr-discussion">antlr-discussion</ulink> mailing list if you compile the code from Git.
            </para>

            <para>
                The master branch
                <programlisting>git clone https://github.com/antlr/antlr4.git</programlisting>
            </para>

            <para>
                Specific branch/tag:
                <programlisting>git clone https://github.com/antlr/antlr4.git
cd antlr4
git checkout -b taged_antlr 4.0</programlisting>
                4.0 is a taged branch in the antlr4 repository
            </para>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="dependencies">
        <title>Autogen.sh</title>
        <para>
            If you are building ANTLR from the distributed source packages,
            then won't need these step.
        </para>
        <para>
            The <command>autogen.sh</command> script can launch
            <command>./configure</command> script automaticaly. In this case
            pass the <command>./configure</command> arguments to the
            <command>./autogen.sh</command> command.
            This will build antlr in the source directory.
        </para>
        <programlisting>./autogen.sh --prefix=/home/antlr/local</programlisting>

        <para>
            It can be a good idea to build the source in a separated directory.
            Tell autogen.sh do not run .configure script :
        </para>
        <programlisting>export NOCONFIGURE=1
./autogen.sh</programlisting>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="dependencies">
        <title>Satisfy the dependencies</title>
        <para>
            On UNIX-like systems ANTLR uses the standard GNU build system,
            using <application>autoconf</application> for package
            configuration and resolving portability issues,
            <application>automake</application> for building makefiles that
            comply with the GNU Coding Standards, and
            <application>libtool</application> for building shared libraries
            on multiple platforms.
        </para>

        <para>
            If you are building ANTLR from the distributed source packages,
            then won't need these tools installed; the necessary pieces
            of the tools are already included in the source packages. But
            it's useful to know a bit about how packages that use these
            tools work.
        </para>

        <para>
            Before you can compile the ANTLR Runtime library, you need to have
            various other tools and libraries installed on your
            system. The two tools needed during the build process (as
            differentiated from the tools used in when creating ANTLR
            mentioned above such as <application>autoconf</application>)
            are <command>pkg-config</command> and GNU make.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <ulink
                    url="http://www.freedesktop.org/software/pkgconfig">pkg-config</ulink>
                    is a tool for tracking the compilation flags needed for
                    libraries that are used by the ANTLR libraries. (For each
                    library, a small <literal>.pc</literal> text file is installed
                    in a standard location that contains the compilation flags
                    needed for that library along with version number information.)
                    <!-- The version of <command>pkg-config</command> needed to build
                    ANTLR is mirrored in the <filename>dependencies</filename> directory
                    on the <ulink url="ftp://ftp.antlr.org/pub/antlr/">ANTLR FTP
                    site.</ulink> -->
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The ANTLR makefiles will mostly work with different versions
                    of <command>make</command>, however, there tends to be
                    a few incompatibilities, so the ANTLR team recommends
                    installing <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/make">GNU
                    make</ulink> if you don't already have it on your system
                    and using it. (It may be called <command>gmake</command>
                    rather than <command>make</command>.)
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      The libraries that ANTLR depends on are maintained separately.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The GLib library provides core functionality
          such as high level data types, Unicode manipulation, and
          an object and type system to C programs. It is available
          from the <ulink url="ftp://ftp.gtk.org/pub/gtk/v2.6/">GTK+ FTP site.</ulink>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/libiconv/">GNU
          libiconv library</ulink> is needed to build GLib if your
          system doesn't have the <function>iconv()</function>
          function for doing conversion between character
          encodings. Most modern systems should have
          <function>iconv()</function>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The libintl library from the <ulink
          url="http://www.gnu.org/software/gettext/">GNU gettext
          package</ulink> is needed if your system doesn't have the
          <function>gettext()</function> functionality for handling
          message translation databases.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        The gtk-doc-tools library from the <ulink
        url="https://www.gtk.org/gtk-doc/">GTK-Doc Project</ulink> is needed if you want generate the documentation API.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="configuration">
    <title>Configure</title>

    <para>
        In the toplevel of the directory <literal>SOURCE_DIRECTORY</literal> that is created, there will be
        a shell script called <filename>configure</filename> which
        you then run to take the template makefiles called
        <filename>Makefile.am</filename> in the package and create
        makefiles customized for your operating system. The <filename>configure</filename>
        script can be passed various command line arguments to determine how
        the package is built and installed. The most commonly useful
        argument is the <systemitem>--prefix</systemitem> argument which
        determines where the package is installed. To install a package
        in <filename>/home/antlr/local</filename> you would run configure as:
    </para>

    <sect3>
        <title>Configure in source directory</title>
            <programlisting>cd SOURCE_DIRECTORY
./configure --prefix=/home/antlr/local</programlisting>
    </sect3>


    <sect3>
        <title>Configure in separated directory</title>
            <programlisting>cd BUILD_RELEASE_DIRECTORY
SOURCE_DIRECTORY/configure --prefix=/home/antlr/local</programlisting>
    </sect3>

    <para>
        A full list of options can be found by running
        <filename>configure</filename> with the
        <systemitem>--help</systemitem> argument. In general, the defaults are
        right and should be trusted.
    </para>

    <para>
        Several environment variables are useful to pass to set before
        running configure. <envar>CPPFLAGS</envar> contains options to
        pass to the C compiler, and is used to tell the compiler where
        to look for include files. The <envar>LDFLAGS</envar> variable
        is used in a similar fashion for the linker. Finally the
        <envar>PKG_CONFIG_PATH</envar> environment variable contains
        a search path that <command>pkg-config</command> (see below)
        uses when looking for for file describing how to compile
        programs using different libraries. If you were installing ANTLR
        dependencies into <filename>/home/antlr/local</filename>, you
        might want to set these variables as:
    </para>
    <programlisting>CPPFLAGS="-I/home/antlr/local/include"
LDFLAGS="-L/home/antlr/local/lib"
PKG_CONFIG_PATH="/home/antlr/local/lib/pkgconfig"
export CPPFLAGS LDFLAGS PKG_CONFIG_PATH</programlisting>
    <para>
        You may also need to set the <envar>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar>
        environment variable so the systems dynamic linker can find
        the newly installed libraries, and the <envar>PATH</envar>
        environment program so that utility binaries installed by
        the various libraries will be found.
    </para>
    <programlisting>LD_LIBRARY_PATH="/home/antlr/local/lib"
PATH="/home/antlr/local/bin:$PATH"
export LD_LIBRARY_PATH PATH</programlisting>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="extra-configuration-options">
  <title>Configuration Options</title>

    <para>
      In addition to the normal options, the
      <command>configure</command> script for the ANTLR library
      supports a number of additional arguments. (Command line
      arguments for the other ANTLR libraries are described in
      the documentation distributed with the those libraries.)

      <cmdsynopsis>
        <command>configure</command>
        <group>
          <arg>--disable-modules=[lipsy|...]</arg>
        </group>
        <group>
          <arg>--enable-modules=[lipsy|...]</arg>
        </group>
        <group>
          <arg>--enable-debug=[no|minimum|yes]</arg>
        </group>
        <group>
          <arg>--disable-visibility</arg>
          <arg>--enable-visibility</arg>
        </group>
        <group>
          <arg>--disable-gtk-doc</arg>
          <arg>--enable-gtk-doc</arg>
        </group>
      </cmdsynopsis>
    </para>


      <formalpara>
        <title><systemitem>--disable-modules and --enable-modules</systemitem></title>

        <para>
         Normally ANTLR will try to build the Lipsy text file format loaders
         as little shared libraries that are loaded on demand.
         The <option>--disable-modules</option> argument indicates that they should
         all be built statically into the ANTLR library instead.
         This is useful for people who need to produce statically-linked binaries.
         If neither <option>--disable-modules</option> nor
         <option>--enable-modules</option> is specified, then the configure script
         will try to auto-detect whether shared modules work on your system.
        </para>
      </formalpara>



    <formalpara>
      <title><systemitem>--enable-debug</systemitem></title>

      <para>
       Turns on various amounts of debugging support. Setting this to 'no'
       disables g_assert(), g_return_if_fail(), g_return_val_if_fail() and
       all cast checks between different object types. Setting it to 'minimum'
       disables only cast checks. Setting it to 'yes' enables
       <link linkend="ANTLR-Debug-Options">runtime debugging</link>.
       The default is 'minimum'.
       Note that 'no' is fast, but dangerous as it tends to destabilize
       even mostly bug-free software by changing the effect of many bugs
       from simple warnings into fatal crashes. Thus
       <option>--enable-debug=no</option> should <emphasis>not</emphasis>
       be used for stable releases of ANTLR.
      </para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara>
      <title><systemitem>--disable-visibility</systemitem> and
        <systemitem>--enable-visibility</systemitem></title>
      <para>
        The option <systemitem>--disable-visibility</systemitem>
        turns off the use of ELF visibility attributes for linking
        optimizations. This makes sense while changing ANTLR itself,
        since the way in which ANTLR uses visibility attributes
        forces a full rebuild of all source files for any header
        modification.
      </para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara>
      <title><systemitem>--disable-gtk-doc</systemitem> and
        <systemitem>--enable-gtk-doc</systemitem></title>

      <para>
        The <application>gtk-doc</application> package is
        used to generate the reference documentation included
        with ANTLR. By default support for <application>gtk-doc</application>
        is disabled because it requires various extra dependencies
        to be installed. If you have
        <application>gtk-doc</application> installed and
        are modifying ANTLR, you may want to enable
        <application>gtk-doc</application> support by passing
        in <systemitem>--enable-gtk-doc</systemitem>. If not
        enabled, pre-generated HTML files distributed with ANTLR
        will be installed.
      </para>
    </formalpara>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="building">
    <title>Compile and test</title>

    <para>
      First make sure that you have the necessary external
      dependencies installed: <command>pkg-config</command>, GNU make,
      and libintl. To get detailed information about building
      these packages, see the documentation provided with the
      individual packages.
      On a Linux system, it's quite likely you'll have all of these
      installed already except for <command>pkg-config</command>.
    </para>

    <para>
        After you've run
        <filename>configure</filename>, you then run the
        <command>make</command> command to build the package and install
        it.
    </para>
    <programlisting>make</programlisting>
    <para>
      If one of the <filename>configure</filename> scripts fails or running
      <command>make</command> fails, look closely at the error
      messages printed; these will often provide useful information
      as to what went wrong. When <filename>configure</filename>
      fails, extra information, such as errors that a test compilation
      ran into, is found in the file <filename>config.log</filename>.
      Looking at the last couple of hundred lines in this file will
      frequently make clear what went wrong. If all else fails, you
      can ask for help on the antlr-discution mailing list.
      See <xref linkend="antlr-resources"/> for more information.
    </para>

    <programlisting>make check</programlisting>
  </sect2>

    <sect2 id="install">
      <title>Install</title>

        <para>
          Then install the ANTLR libraries in the order:
          GLib then ANTLR. For each library, follow the
          steps of <literal>configure</literal>, <literal>make</literal>,
          <literal>make install</literal> mentioned above. If you're
          lucky, this will all go smoothly, and you'll be ready to
          <link linkend="antlr-compiling">start compiling your own ANTLR
            applications</link>. You can test your ANTLR installation
          by running the <command>antlr-demo</command> program that
          ANTLR installs.
        </para>

        <programlisting>make install</programlisting>

        <para>
            If you don't have permission to write to the directory you are
            installing in, you may have to change to root temporarily before
            running <literal>make install</literal>. Also, if you are
            installing in a system directory, on some systems (such as
            Linux), you will need to run <command>ldconfig</command> after
            <literal>make install</literal> so that the newly installed
            libraries will be found.
        </para>

      <!--para>in the system</para>
      <para>
      in local:
        antlr.pc
        PKG_CONFIG_PATH
        LD_LIBRARY_PATH
        The goal of installation is to use it as :
        gcc `pkg-config - -libs - -cflags antlr-4.0` hello.c
      </para>
      <para>threedparty of project</para-->
    </sect2>


    <sect2 id="uninstall">
        <title>Uninstall</title>
        <para>
            After <command>make</command> or <command>make check</command>
            you can remove the program binaries and object files from the
            build directory by typing :
            <programlisting>make clean</programlisting>
        </para>

        <para>
            To also remove the
            files that <command>configure</command> created (so you can compile the package for
            a different kind of computer), type :
            <programlisting>make distclean</programlisting>
        </para>

        <para>
            There is also a <command>make maintainer-clean</command> target, but that is intended mainly
            for the package's developers.  If you use it, you may have to get
            all sorts of other programs in order to regenerate files that came
            with the distribution.
        </para>

        <para>
            After <command>make install</command>. Often, you can also type
            <command>make uninstall</command> to remove the installed
            files again.
            <programlisting>make uninstall</programlisting>
        </para>
    </sect2>

</sect1>
